I
suck you ever said that to yourself good
chance you've got something called
impostor
syndrome and this goes along with
another video I'd made about not calling
yourself
Junior let the people decide for
themselves whether you're junior by
telling them how much how many years of
experience what you've done let them
make the decision not you I'm here to
tell you that you don't probably suck as
bad as you think you do but let's jump
into this what does impostor syndrome
even mean what is impostor syndrome I'm
searching this just like you could from
the command line impostor syndrome
impostor syndrome is the psychological
experience of feeling like a fake or a
phony despite any genuine success you
have
achieved um learn about hey hey I don't
even know I don't this is not a I'm not
advocating for these people at all they
were just the first hit um you may have
impost if you find yourself consistently
experiencing self-doubt even in areas
where you typically Excel impostor
syndrome may feel like nervousness
accompanied by the belief that you found
you're being found out oh no they know
that I actually suck negative selft talk
depression all of this we go through
this all the time imposter system
syndrome is not a diagnosed mental
illness instead of the term is usually
narrow applied to intelligence and
achievement although it also has links
to perfectionism and social context all
right so we we could talk about that a
lot more than that but the real Crux of
this is in in when it comes to
technology it is very easy to get
impostor syndrome and you read about
this I remember Sarah drner a very
successful technologist um uh once
commented on this uh in Twitter saying
this saying that they were struggling
with it even know that they're very well
established um and the the honestly if
you're feeling like you might not
measure up it's probably a good thing um
there going to make another video about
something called Anakin syndrome uh or
dun and Krueger effect and cognitive
dissonance and all that kind of stuff
those are all much much worse I if you
think that you suck there's a good
chance you're going to try harder and
you're going to go longer and you're
going to do you know the extra
uh research to do the thing so however I
did also do a video based on Larry
Wall's Virtues Of An engineer uh
laziness impatience and hubris huis
being a pejorative word that usually
means full of arrogance um so you know
you can take that as you will but I
think it's safe to say that the way to
overcome impostor syndrome is to gain an
accurate measure of what you can can do
by doing those things we talked in
another video about writing down your
skill stack very simple uh practice to
to measure what you know and what you
don't know and to evaluate yourself and
in another video how to supplement your
understanding of your own skills with
input from others
specifically your Mentor or two and your
the other number two person in your
world your recruiter recruiters are paid
to pump you up they are paid to make you
feel good about yourself and a good
recruiter will help you banish imposture
syndrome because they help reflect to
you what you actually know they'll be
the first people to tell you not to call
yourself a junior not so they can get
more money placing you with an
organization but because they have been
around and they know what it means to
evaluate yourself uh in an honest light
based on your experience and the stuff
that that you can actually do um so
another thing about impostor syndrome
that really helps and this is a personal
U story um I remember once upon a time I
know sit down let's get the copy okay
once upon a time I was hired to be
Nike's internal internet web Master my
job was to build and support the entire
internal website for the all of the
company of Nike Nike this wasn't
nike.com this was swet and although I
wasn't responsible for installing the
servers and everything I was responsible
in helping every single Department in
the entire company get their content
online and it was a very overwhelming
thing it made me feel like oh I couldn't
do it and if I hadn't come from another
place where I teleport where I had done
amazing things that knew I had done then
I would have been more nervous about it
but even then despite all that I still
constantly felt like God I could I need
to learn more I need to learn more and
that drove me to stay up late at night
learning things like Java which was
relevant back then in 1990 whatever um
and I spent a lot of time doing that um
and I also knew that I needed to kind of
constantly I was like I'm missing
something you know there's something I
probably don't know I remember being
really self-conscious about not knowing
SQL uh standard query language which is
big for databases and at the time in the
90s the integration of databases with
websites became like the coolest thing
ever I know it's like a standard thing
now but back then that was the big thing
if you had a datadriven database backed
website you know uh you were you know
all the rid and you know side Side Story
that's you know PHP you have to have a
database to even use it right well that
WordPress and stuff like that got big at
the time when everything was database
driven that's changed now a little bit
so that was the thing and I I feel like
I didn't know SQL and so I got sent to
um a training session I get they my boss
I think paid something like $2500 for me
to spend a week in Seattle uh at a psql
conference I think I've told the story
before in another video but I'm going to
repeat it and and I was there and I went
through my time and I studied really
hard and I felt really guilty because my
young wife with her to with our toddlers
was home you know off in raising dollars
by herself while I was on it big prum so
I really jumped into it and learned hard
and I came back and actually there was a
couple other people there who really
didn't
care and they were like always late and
they didn't do anything and you know and
they got the same certificate as me and
they went home to and every and I got
back and I was like okay we all it just
it dawned on me on the plane while we
were flying back I was like we all we
all got this same certificate and I just
realized how broken the whole system was
but the you know impostor syndrome is
what drove me to even ask for the
training so I could go do it um but then
after I had that experience I went back
and I proceeded to tell um my manager
it's like I never ever want to do
another training like that it's a total
waste of money I said but I would like
to propose something can I use half of
the money and buy per year and put that
money towards buying books specifically
and 1990s O'Reilly books and I we had
Pal's books which is a you know
nationally renowned bookstore in in
Portland Oregon and I went in there and
she goes yes absolutely and I went in
there and I bought a wall full of books
and I had this wall of ailly books in my
cubicle not to flex but to support me
and the reason I'm telling you this
story is because knowing I had at the
time you got understand the internet was
still pretty new there was no Google yet
Yahoo had just barely started to get you
know to be useful and people were still
regularly turning to book content um in
order to supplement their actual skills
um that's largely changed today but the
but the idea is the same in order for me
to get over my impostor syndrome I had
to learn and by having the safety net of
a wall of books that I could pull out in
any time and I could go look up what I
needed to learn something I call Just in
Time learning which is you know there's
no way you can keep it all on your head
at the same time and and you know the
other virtues patience laziness and you
know laziness and impatience those
virtues make you not want to put things
in your head that can be looked up and
so by having this entire wall of stuff
to go to I Knew really quickly that I
could go find whatever I needed from the
world's you know experts at the time in
those Technologies and and and I felt
much more safe much more capable and my
impostor syndrome was obliterated at
that point um in fact to the point where
I knew that I could do anything I was
called upon given the enough time and
the enough you know U and this is a
repeat of another video that I said but
Darlene the malware coder said given the
amount given the the enough time and wi
papers I can run circles around any
Security Site software and I felt that
you know that's hubris right that's huus
that's a good good thing um and but you
know I I could have said the same thing
after I had that wall of Riley books
given enough time and the write a Riley
book I can do anything I can literally
do anything and that becomes huous it's
the opposite of impostor syndrome I
never became so arrogant to the point at
least I don't think where you know I
would tell people they were dumb for not
being able to do it I just knew that I
could to defeat the impostor syndrome
because I knew where to go so the the
the the solution to impostor syndrome is
two things and the other the other one I
haven't talked about yet the first one
is well three things really having the
skills I mean if you have the Baseline
impostor syndrome I mean the skills that
are doing it then your imposter syndrome
goes away number two having the
resources available at your beck and
call to Justin Time whether it's a book
or a zle Casten which we'll talk about
in another video or a bunch of notes uh
and the third having a professional
Learning Network uh I cannot overstate
how important having a professional
Learning Network is and that's going to
be its own video um but that is the
other main way to combat impostor
syndrome this is you can go out to your
chat you can ask well what is the best
thing I should go look up here and you
can find those things and I regularly
use my twitch Community for this very
thing um you know it's um you know you
go to them whether it be for job leads
or you have a question about what is the
best way to deal with you know private
GitHub intersource uh repos that can't
be built with go which is a very
relevant thing that happened this last
couple weeks so those are the methods of
of fighting against imposter syndrome